Urofsky, Melvin; Papers ua902.022
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Melvin Urofsky Papers
1850-1978
1870-1940
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Urofsky, Melvin I.
ua902.022
14.83 cubic ft.
The Melvin Urofsky Papers discuss his research and editing of his multi-volume series on the letters of Louis Brandeis. The papers consist of copies of Brandeis' letters, drafts of the volumes co-edited by Urofsky, and several of Urofsky's notebooks.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Donated to the University Archives by Melvin Urofsky in 1972-1974 and 1977.
Biographical History
Dr. Melvin Urofsky was born in February of 1939. He earned his Ph.D. in American history from Columbia University in 1968 after getting his M.A. in American history in 1962 from Columbia University and his B.A. in history in 1961 from Columbia College.
While Urofsky was earning his doctorate he worked as an history instructor at Ohio State University. He became an assistant professor of history and education at the State University of New York (SUNY) at Albany in 1967 and worked there for three years. In 1972 Urofsky joined the History Department faculty at the James E. Allen Jr. Collegiate Center at SUNY Albany. Later he joined the faculty of Virginia Commonwealth University where he now serves as a professor of law and public policy and professor emeritus of history.
During his career, Dr. Urofsky has published more than a dozen books. With David Levy, he co-edited a five volume series of Supreme Court Justice Louis D. Brandeis' letters, including Urban Reformer 1807-1907 in 1971, People's Attorney 1907-1912 in 1972, and Progressive and Zionist 1913-1915 in 1973. Urofsky has also published numerous articles in various journals throughout his career, many on the subject of Zionism and Brandeis as well as law and the Supreme Court.
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of mostly copies of Louis Brandeis' letters. The letters are dated from roughly 1870 to about 1940, but the photocopies were most likely made by Urofsky for the purposes of writing his series on the letters. As the date of the photocopying is not known, the dates of creation of the letters are the ones used for description purposes. There are several outlying dates within the correspondence photocopies; they pertain to documents written by Urofsky about the books and the letters, they are not the dates of the Brandeis letters themselves.
Aside from the photocopies, the collection also contains drafts of the first three volumes in a loose-page format, several notebooks of Urofsky's, and two galleys separated into an oversize box for proper preservation and storage. The materials seem to pertain only to the first three volumes of Louis Brandeis' letters, not any other Brandeis publication by Urofsky or the last two volumes in the series.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series. It is arranged alphabetically.
Public Servants; Zionism; Judges--United States--Correspondence; Correspondence; Photocopies; Galley proofs; Notebooks; Urofsky, Melvin I.; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941
- Correspondence, Amy, Undated (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence 1850-1969, 1877-1880; 1882-1894; 1933-1939 (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence 1871-1880, 1876-1880 (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence 1880-1889, 1880-1882; 1886-1889 (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Evans Mss., 1890-1894; Undated (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence 1890-1899, 1890-1894; 1896-1899 (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1900 March-December (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1901 January-June; 1901 September-December (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1902 January-May (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1902 May-December (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1903 January-July; 1903 September; 1903 December (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1904 January-July (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1904 July-December (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1905 January-March (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1905 March-June (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1905 July-September (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1905 September-November (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1905 November-December (Box 1 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1906 January-April (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1906 May-July (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1906 July (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1906 August-October (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1906 November (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1906 December (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1907 January-March (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1907 March-April (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1907 May-June (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1907 July-September (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1907 October-December (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1908 January-March (Box 2 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1908 April-May (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1908 June-August; 1971 April (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1908 September-December (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1909 January-March (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1909 April-May (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1909 June-August (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1909 September-December (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1910 January-March (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1910 April-June (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1910 July-September (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1910 October-December (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1911 January-May (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1911 June-July (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1911 August-September (Box 3 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1911 October-December (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1912 January-February (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1912 March-April (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1912 May-June (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1912 July-August (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1912 September (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1912 October (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1912 November (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1912 December (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1913 January (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1913 February (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1913 March (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1913 April (Box 4 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1913 May (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1913 June (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1913 July 1-19 (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1913 July 20-31; 1913 August (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1913 September (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1913 October (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1913 November-December (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1914 January-February (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1914 March-July (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1914 August-September (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1914 October 1-15 (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1914 October 16-31 (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1914 November 1-15 (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1914 November 16-30 (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1914 December (Box 5 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1915 January (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1915 February (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1915 March 1-15 (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1915 March 16-31 (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1915 April-May (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1915 June (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1915 July (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1915 August (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1915 September (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1915 October (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1915 November (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1915 December (Box 6 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1916 January (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1916 February 1-19 (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1916 February 20 March 10 (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1916 March 11-31 (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1916 April (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1916 May 1-20 (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1916 May 21-June 10 (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1916 June 11-20 (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1916 June 21-30 (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1916 July-August (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1916 September-December (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1917 January-March (Box 7 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1917 April-May (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1917 June-August (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1917 September-October (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1917 November-December (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1918 January-February (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1918 March-June (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1918 July-September (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1918 October (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1918 November-December (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1919 January-February (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1919 March-April (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1919 May (Box 8 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1919 June-July (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1919 August-October (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1919 November-December (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1920 January-February (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1920 March-April (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1920 May-July (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1920 August-September (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1920 October-November 15 (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1920 November 16- December (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1921 January-March (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1921 April-June (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1921 July-August (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1921 September-October (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1921 November-December (Box 9 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1922 January-April (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1922 May-December (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1923 January-June (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1923 July-December (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1924 January-June (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1924 July-December (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1925 January-June (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1925 July-December (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1926 January-March (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1926 April-June (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1926 July-December (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1927 January-June (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1927 July-December (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1928 January-May (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1928 June-December (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1929 January-July (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1929 August-December (Box 10 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1930 January-May (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1930 June-July (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1930 August (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1930 September (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1930 October-November (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1930 December (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1931 January-June (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1931 July-December (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1932 January-June (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1932 July-December (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1933 January-June (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1933 July-December (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1934 January-June (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1934 July-December (Box 11 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1935 January-June (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1935 July-December (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1936 January-June (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1936 July-December (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1937 (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1938 January-June (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1938 July-December (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1939 January-April (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1939 May-September (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1939 October-December (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1940 January-April (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1940 May-August (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1940 September-December (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1941 January-May (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1941 June-October (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 15)
- Correspondence, Additions, 1902-1920; 1934-1941; 1976-1978; Undated (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 16)
- Galley of Brandeis Letters Volume III, Undated (Oversized 1)
- Galley of Brandeis Letters Volume III, Undated (Oversized 1)
- The Letters of Louis Dembitz Brandeis, Additions to Volume I, 1869-1907 (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 17)
- Letters of Louis Dembitz Brandeis, Volume I Part I, 1870-1902 (Box 12 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 18)
- Letters of Louis Dembitz Brandeis, Volume I Part II, 1902-1905 (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Letters of Louis Dembitz Brandeis, Volume I Part III, 1906-1907 (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume II Part II, 1908 June-1910 December (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume II Part III, 1911 (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume II Part IV, 1912 (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume III Running Register, 1913 January-1915 December (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume III Progressive and Zionist Part I, 1913 January-June (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume III Progressive and Zionist Part II, 1913 July-1914 September (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume III Progressive and Zionist Part III, 1914 October-1915 April (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume III Progressive and Zionist Part IV, 1915 May-December (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume II Running Register, 1907-1912 (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume II Part I, 1907 July-1908 May (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Letters of Louis D. Brandeis, Volume III Run-through, Final, Undated (Box 13 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Notebook, Undated (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 1)
- Notebook Number 1, Undated (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 2)
- Notebook Number 2, Undated (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 3)
- Notebook Volume II Parts II and IV, Undated (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 4)
- Notebook Volume III, 1913-1915 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 5)
- Notebook Volume IV, 1916-1921 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 6)
- Publication Announcement Reviews, Urofsky, Melvin, 1968-1972 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 7)
- Strum, Philippa, Brandeis and the Exercise of Judicial Power Draft, 1977 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 8)
- Typescript III Pages 1-159, 1913 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 9)
- Typescript III Pages 160-329, 1913 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 10)
- Typescript III Pages 330-499, 1913 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 11)
- Typescript III Pages 500-649, 1913-1914 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 12)
- Typescript III Pages 650-799, 1914 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 13)
- Typescript III Pages 800-969, 1914 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 14)
- Typescript III Pages 970-1149, 1914-1915 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 15)
- Typescript III Pages 1150-1349, 1915 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 16)
- Typescript III Pages 1350-1511, 1915 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 17)
- Typescript III Pages 1512-1711, 1915 (Box 14 (Melvin Urofsky Papers), Folder 18)